My name is Jacqueline Montanez, aka Loca
D. I was convicted of a double murder in
1992, sentenced to life in prison as a
juvenile. I served 31 years in prison at
a maximum women's prison in Illinois.
This is how crime works.
You got domestic violence in there. You
got girlfriends beating on girlfriends,
stabbing them. I was like, "Oh, I'm
going to die here. I'm going to die. My
mouth alone is going to get me killed."
A women's max security prison is all
women.
Everybody's serving over 20 some years
for crimes, really hard crimes, murders,
drug trafficking, sexual trafficking,
all sorts of stuff like that. 10 to 15%
of women in prison are in truly a
maximum security for serious cases. My
stepfather was very abusive.
Um he was training me to be a female hit
woman. Everything that he taught me and
trained me
to do I used it against him. I ended up
killing two of his gang members. When
they gave me life in prison, they took
me straight to Dwight Correctional
Facility in Illinois. I was 17 years
old, the youngest in prison.
I remember my first day in prison, I
knew nothing to expect from this place.
Here I am a gang leader.
I sentenced to life in prison. I just
killed two people and I should be tough.
Instead, the girl in me came out. The
little kid came out and I was scared to
death. I was like, "These people out
here going to kill me." Went to see the
doctors and everybody kept looking at
me. But before I was being released to
go on grounds,
a few of the lifers, there was three of
them, and they brought me a big old bag
of clothes and TVs and I was like, "Oh,
no, these people trying to make me their
girl." But they explained to me who they
were and they told me that they were
lifers and and they gave me a knife.
And they told me, "Prepare yourself.
You're going to see a lot of things and
they're going to try They're going to
try to try you. So, you have to stand
your ground." And I'm like, "Okay.
Okay." And I remember
um going to the yard and I got
surrounded by a whole bunch of Latin
Kings. And I was like, "Oh, okay, here
we go." There was one particular old
lady there and she was sitting in front
of me. She was cussing me out. My
reaction was to react, but one thing
I knew my mother always taught me
respect your elders. And second, she
stated that she was the auntie of one of
the men that I had killed.
So, I had to I just got I just lowered
my head in respect. You know what I'm
saying? Out of respect. And as y'all she
kept saying was, "You killed my nephew.
Um you're going to die here. Woo woo
woo." And then there was a lady next to
her
who wasn't older
and uh she called herself and I was
like, "Oh yeah, we going to get it." She
was actually a Latin King. Latin Kings
and Latin Queens are the number one
rivals of the Maniac Latin Disciples.
And she had killed a Maniac before. So,
that's what she was there for. At that
moment, that day, I said, "Okay, Loca D,
you have to come out and you have to
take over. It's no more Jacqueline, it's
no more Jackie. Loca D had to be the one
that's in prison." So, I did that. I let
Loca D come out and I became the most
fearful
person in Dwight. Loca D is my gang
name. It's In English, it's crazy
disciple. That's what it stands for. I
had a reputation to uphold. I was a
chief of the Maniacs. I threw up my gang
signs and she's They started throwing up
their gang signs. But when I threw up my
gang signs, a lot of G a lot of the GDs
and the Maniacs and all the folks came.
And then the officers came like, "Break
it up." And they walked me out the the
circle. All of a sudden, I see a splash
of blood come on me. I'm like, "What the
Did I just get stabbed or something?"
And I looked and it was a couple in the
side slicing each other's face. I was
like, "Oh, I'm going to die here." I did
not want to go through what I went
through the first day. I had to show
that I was not fearful and I had to show
that I was not to be messed with. I did
end up stabbing somebody. I did. Just
And the girl didn't even do nothing to
me. When I first moved into the dorm,
people were raping somebody in the
closet and I had walked by. And I'm
seeing her getting beat.
And I was like, "Oh,
okay. This is the time I have to prove
myself.
Cuz if not, it's going to be me in that
closet.
So, I went in my room, put my bags down,
pulled out my shank,
went down the hallway,
and walked into that closet.
And I snapped. I got to swinging. Let go
of that damn girl. What the hell is
wrong with y'all?
And I just got to snapping. So, I'm end
up fighting these people.
And that made a name for me. That really
did make a name for me. I end up going
to Kankakee for 6 months.
And
that everybody got to knowing who Loco D
was.
Everybody knew who Loco D was. So, I
wasn't to be messed with. There was
times where I was tough and cute and
everything during the day, and then as
soon as the night came, I was crying
like a baby.
And I was crying for my mom, and I was
asking God, "Please send me home. I'm
sorry. I want to I really believe that
they would just want to hear me say
sorry, and they would let me go home."
I've done nothing but max. I've been in
a maximum um women's prison. They sent
me all the way to Florida. So, I went to
a low correctional facility. I went to
Homestead. Um it was a dorms. I slept
with 87 women
in a dorm situation. In Illinois, it's
two-man cells. So, it wasn't as as much
as it is in Florida. In Dwight, we have
fences. It was a inside fence wired.
They they do security like that, but not
as much. Decatur
was no fence at all. They they were able
to
damn near walk their visitor to the car.
But, it's ironic because
you had more escape attempts in Dwight
than you did Decatur. We had a inmate
sent to the authority came from Decatur
to work at Dwight cuz she's worked
inside grounds. Literally escaped from
Dwight Correctional Facility. Was gone.
We was on lockdown.
Um
it was so And I couldn't believe this
lady had escaped. I was like, "What the
She wasn't even a lifer." She was going
home in less than a month. She did get
caught months later.
Um somebody told on her. said she was
where she was at and she was arrested,
charged with escape.
And then we had another
situation where we had a lifer.
She went and dyed her clothes,
dyed a hat, and made herself look like a
visitor, and walked out with the
visitors.
So, I mean, they do have attempts,
though. They have
They do have a quite a few escape
attempts.
I think it might have crossed one time
when I was in the county hospital.
When I was at the county hospital and
they left me standing right there, not
shackled, not handcuffed, not nothing,
and I was just standing right there, too
close to the front door.
And it passed my mind. I was like, do
you know
I'm right here in Chicago
and I can just so easily go.
And I kept thinking that like,
what do I do? What do I do? What do What
should I do? What should I do?
And I didn't do it cuz I was scared. I
was like, they're going to have me on
America's Most Wanted. They're going to
I'm going to be everywhere. I was like,
no, no, let's just let it go. Let it go.
It's okay. But, a lot of people take the
chances and they take it.
Officers did bring in stuff we sold for
them.
They would bring us drugs and or um
really that country, man, they sold more
pills down there. The psychotropic meds
or seizure meds in Illinois. But, when I
was in Florida prison, that's where the
real drugs were at. It's ridiculous.
The officers were bringing in super
drugs.
They were bringing coke, cane, heroin,
they were bringing anything. You were
selling drugs down there for the
officers.
Um, the officers were bringing
cigarettes, they were bringing K2. They
were bring That was prison. Dwight and
Logan was nothing compared to Low
Correction Facility, man. You name it.
Florida prison, we can have somebody
drop it off in the parking lot, and then
one of the workers will go pick it up
and bring it in.
So, it was a lot easier. They do give us
state pay, but state pay is like
$15 a month. Nothing. $15 won't get you
na- nothing.
Um when it comes out to your personals
and food. They got out of family. My
family still bought me none of my gang
members did. I never received not a
dollar from either one of them.
But my mother did. So I was blessed to
as far as commissary is concerned. But
for those of who don't have people
sending them money, people is robbing
people's boxes.
You'll go to school and come back and
your lock box is popped and you lost all
your food. They even robbed commissary.
We was They was down there rehearsing
for a show and popped the commissary
door open and robbed the whole
commissary. I worked in the kitchen.
Um I was a house girl where you clean in
the house area. The only job that you
could really make money on was industry.
They were making the men's clothes, they
were making the women's clothes. You had
to get approval to go in there. So a lot
of people wouldn't approve.
You had to be something to work in there
cuz not just anybody would could work
there.
The race dynamics in um the supermax
prisons or the max prisons for women,
we do tend to be the Hispanics and the
blacks tend to stick together. The white
girls are always the vics.
They're the ones with the money, they're
the ones that you can scare. You know
what I'm saying? But don't get it
twisted cuz I didn't get whooped by a
white girl.
How about my girlfriend? It surprised
the hell out of me. So I never
underestimate none of them. But they do
have it to where
it's the white girls are the are the
lords of the institution and the
Hispanics and the black ones feel like
they run that [__] Like if I want to
get moved in the in the same dorm with
my girlfriend, I can go tell another
inmate and pay her. Like hey, help me
get moved to this dorm. Next thing you
know, they was calling me. My turn is
backing up, you're moving move move
move. I was like, for real? I only had
to pay her $50. Like
you got these women, we run that [__]
>> Is there violence in women's prisons and
why?
>> There is a violence in women's prison.
Violence is there. No matter what they
say, oh
prisons maximum prisons in Illinois
don't have Yes, the hell we do. They
just don't report them.
This was actually maximum prison for
women and it was not nothing like what
they show on TV. The gangs in women
prison is totally different than in
men's prison. The gang banging stuff is
not as tough as the guys have it. I
mean, we don't gang bang as much, but
they're there. They're there. Um we had
the chief of the of the GDs there. Um
me, the chief of the Queens, um we had a
lot of Vice Lords. We had a lot of gang
members. The women's maximum prison is
more about relationships. They fight
about relationships. Girl on girl, you
messing with my girl, that's my woman,
woo woo.
You got domestic violence in there. You
got girlfriends beating on girlfriends.
Cutting them up. Slicing their face.
Stabbing them. I I I cut a girl up for
having sex with my girlfriend. We'll
take the mop, you know how you have the
mop stick? It has the metal piece. We'll
take that metal piece and we'll sharpen
it up on the floor, on the cement
outside, and that becomes a shank.
Um I've had a toothbrush shave you you
you're shaving it up and that becomes a
shank. You take the blade off the razor.
You put it on the toothbrush, becomes a
shank. It's it's rough when it comes to
that. I can say that I my years in
Dwight Correctional Center was the
hardest and it became my home.
And I got to accept that I was going to
die there. The those were going to be
the same walls I see when I lose take my
last breath.
There's a lot of violence there and it
doesn't have to necessarily be gangs.
The officers jumping on you, raping you.
I had set my room on fire because they
had a officer there that was not
supposed to work there. He used to call
us B words all the time. He said, "Women
are no good. All they're good for is to
to have sex and suck." He got on there
and was like, "You're not running
nothing, woo woo."
I was like, "Oh,
So, I tied my door down and set my room
on fire.
So, they had to come and I had a sock
full of double D batteries.
He came in and he swung and hit me dead
in my eye.
And when he hit me in my eye, I let
loose.
I got to beating him with a sock full of
batteries.
Um another officer came and grabbed my
arm.
Officer McCluster, he grabbed my arm and
in the process of him grabbing my arm,
the sock went back and broke his jaw.
Um by him catching a case, they gave me
7 and 1/2 years for that extra, added on
to my life sentence. The women ran the
prisons in Illinois prison. We ran it.
But in Florida prison, I couldn't I was
fearful. I I I I didn't even want to go
down there and tell them who I was. I
didn't want to tell them what my gang
name was because when I saw the way that
them people were being treated, you end
up dead, beats, and all types of stuff.
It was tough down there. I I went to a
low correction facility and I was in the
main unit. Actually, a inmate was
paralyzed from a officer. I've watched
one inmate go up to the gate to ask
officer a question and she got tasered,
maced,
and slammed on the head.
But
we have more violence against each other
and that's sick and that's really sick.
The male officers are like they fall for
they try to have sex with all the
inmates. They try to have sex with all
the staff. They don't care. They think
that when we're sentenced to prison,
that we become their slaves. That we
become
we have to do what they say, regardless.
They give us a direct order and we have
to do it. They just think that they're
just glorified, but [__] can happen to
them, too.
So it it it was a mixture. I was
actually in the county jail. I got
married to an inmate or officer. It was
a little jailhouse marriage, marriage,
but
she I got her name on my back. She got
my name on her neck.
She had me She got bought me a ring,
a real ring.
And it was like we had a little ceremony
in the library.
So, I mean, if I had consensual cuz I
was in love with this lady. So, you do
have consensual relationships. 2008 was
a big year for for the officers to lose
their job. We had a big prostitution
ring in the white. I was involved with a
female officer and people were getting
paid them them inmates were getting paid
food from the kitchen from the from the
kitchen. Shrimps. They was They were
having sex for for extra food. And some
people were having sex for food for
money. When we made the newspaper, a lot
of us was in confinement. DOJ came
through and
they weren't playing. They did a full
investigation and a lot of officers lost
their job because they were forcing
inmates have sex with them. Even if it
wasn't against the law
because even if I it was a consensual
relationship, it still was against the
law because I'm an inmate and I have to
be protected by law and you're an
officer and you're supposed to protect
me. After the prostitution ring happened
in the white,
they had to start to to put video
cameras up because they they didn't have
proof in the first day but they knew it
was happening. So, they had they were
not having no other choice but to put up
cameras. So, now we had cameras
everywhere in the institution. We were
being watched. Officers don't mess with
the men prisons like prisons like they
do us. It's a totally different thing.
Um like they can be so aggressive with
us versus the men that's going to tell
their asses. They can do what they want
to do.
I just think that the men's prison is
more dangerous.
Way more dangerous than a women's prison
like
we got incidents but they got problems.
The men's prison, when they get caught
talking to officer, you snitching and
you going to get dealt with. You do not
survive. The men's will take care of the
other men's will beat beat them. Now, if
you get if you're being sent to IA and
settle fast and you go there a lot,
you're a snitch. As time goes by, they
they makes hanging with the prison
officer a lot, doing favors for them and
and kicking with them. They They click.
They click like real people and they
they are able to go in there and say,
um move her over here or move her up.
They're able to do that.
Well, And uh prison, you have the
girlfriend on girlfriend. It is against
the rules though. You're not supposed to
be in a relationship. I mean, when it
comes down to having sex, make put a
curtain over your bed, lock the door,
have a lookout. You're not supposed to
do it in prison, but we do. If you got
caught, you're going to confinement.
Confinement is the same thing as
solitary. You're going down for a
sexual. A sexual carries First sexual
carry 15 days in confinement. Um a month
C grade, which is C grade. You can't use
the phone. You got no commissary. But
you could only shop full access is when
you're A grade.
So, well, definitely, if we get caught
doing anything with a in a
relationship-wise,
you're going to combine and you're
getting C grade. Everybody
who came through F say used to be like,
"Jackie want to dance." Jackie want to
dance. She the finest Puerto Rican down
there. Cuz I was the youngest and I was
the finest. I was fresh meat. Everybody
wanted to have sex Jackie want to dance.
And I was the type until I learned till
the nurse pulled me to the side and told
me,
"You're going to catch AIDS." That
stopped me.
That was it. It was over for me. I was
like, "Oh, my whole days are over. I'm
going to retire. I'm in retirement." So,
it was it was hard. It was hard because
like I said, you have your relationships
I had a wife on every door. And you you
share partners a lot. So, that's why I
thank God that I never caught nothing
because I could have.
You go through heartbreak. You really go
through heartbreak. Um I used to think
that
my relationships were my sentence for
committing a crime.
Having life in prison was not a bother
for me.
I was okay with having life in prison.
I I was fine. Prison is not a a issue.
This That's a world inside of another
world. You still have sex. You still
look good. You still wear clothes. You
still wear shoes. So, there was nothing
I was missing out here in free world.
I think my sentence was falling in love
so many times and be left in prison.
Or being cheated on. Or being told,
"You're never going home. So, I don't
want you. What I want you for?" It's
family oriented in there. Like they We
try to find our family since we don't
have our family with us. I had a prison
mom, I had a prison dad, I had prison
kids, aunties, uncles. The boy girls
being a father or uncle or brother. A
lot of us were lifers. Me personally, I
had my mother
love her to death, but she's the one
that taught me
how to be a woman.
Like I said, I went I got incarcerated
at 15. So, I didn't know how to be a
woman. She taught me the way life is,
what to do and what not to do. But, I
didn't have so many kids and and so many
aunties and uncles and you build it
there. You build it there. You build
your family there, and they love you for
real. Like, they really are your family
member.
Since I was a child, one of my always
wanted to be a police officer.
But, I ended up being one of the bad
guys. My stepfather was very abusive. Um
he was training me to be a female hit
woman.
His former training was rape and
beatings and all this other stuff. So, I
was kind of forced to be in a gang.
That's why I was in the neighborhood of
Latin Kings.
He was the um white hand man of Lord
Gino.
He was training me to be a female hit
woman.
He wanted me to be so tough. I didn't
have Barbies, I didn't have teddy bears.
I had none of that. I had knives and
guns, learned how to cook drugs.
Everything that he taught me and trained
me
to do, I used it against him. I ended up
killing two of his gang members. So, my
life was supposed to be for Latin Queen.
I was supposed to be a Latin Queen.
But, I ended up being a Maniac Latin
Disciple. Because I didn't want to go
with my stepfather. My stepfather
was a rapist. He raped me, he beat me,
took me where they'd beat me and rape me
as well, touching.
So, I was being taught to hate, to
really hate people, not to show no type
of love. So, because of that, I joined
their oppositional gang.
Which was the Maniac Latin Disciples. My
best friend was murdered. He was
murdered in my car.
I believe the bullet was intended for
me, cuz he was in my car.
So, I retaliated.
I did not kill innocent people.
I killed the people that pulled the
trigger and it was involved.
So that's what I tell my brothers. I
wish I could switch switch places with
them. At first I wasn't remorseful. When
I got a sentence I wasn't remorseful and
everybody saw that. During the whole
trial I did not cry and I shed one tear.
I tried to fight the judge. I spit on
him, told the state attorney I was going
to kill him and his family if I ever get
out. Woo, I had no type of remorse.
None.
When I was told that I was going to get
life in prison I broke down like a child
and hit the floor. My co-defendant was
sentenced to death, Marilyn Melero.
They've been home free with wrongful
conviction. Their conviction has been
overturned.
Um they have been acquitted of the
charges cuz I took the weight. I regret
what I did.
I do. Um
I took somebody's father, brother, son
away.
And that's something that I have to live
with. I have nightmares. I still picture
me shooting him. I still see the blood.
This is something I did. So
I'm sorry that people don't want me
home. I'm sorry that there's a lot of
people feel that I should still be a
prisoner. At first I did too.
But now with the achievements that I'm
making and and and the growth that I'm
showing, I feel like I deserve a second
chance. Um
I can't bring them boys back. I can't.
But I have to live with that for the
rest of my life. I've been free for 4
years now. 4 years I've been free.
And I'm telling you I still feel it
today.
I've actually spoken to a cousin
and a nephew.
Um
I've give I was given a chance to
apologize to them.
Um the rest of family does not want to
have anything to do with me.
Um and that's understandable.
The pregnant women they get a different
color shirt. Like they'll give a pink
top to show that they're they're
pregnant. They do get the bottom bunk.
Extra meals. They get They're get fine
if you ask me. They still get messed
with, but it's just to let people know
yeah that that person is pregnant. And
the only time you get pregnant in prison
is if you come in prison pregnant. So,
you did relation with officer or you
were raped by an officer. That's the
only way you're getting pregnant.
They'll get to get to the doctors and
they'll get to have their little things,
but they're they're more they're more
taken care of than the regular inmates.
I mean, some people some girls
accidentally get birth in prison. Like
sometimes your water back break. You
never know when it breaks. So, some girl
had a baby in the toilet. You know what
I'm saying? So, it happens. But usually
usually, they're supposed to take you
out in the ambulance. They'll take you
out and take you to the hospital and you
give birth to your baby. You stay there
for like 2 days with the baby and then
you have somebody come pick up the baby.
If there's nobody there to pick them up,
DCFS will take over.
My personal experience was I was never
able to even
look at mines. So, I didn't experience
nothing like that. I was in confinement
the whole time. Actually in the mental
health unit. They put me in the mental
health unit um
where nobody can see me, but
mine was really hush hush because I
didn't want to do what they wanted me to
do. They wanted me to have abortion. You
got some inmates too who agreed of well,
if you trust me, I'll have an abortion.
A lot of them agreed with that.
I wasn't I wasn't one of them. They
wanted to give me psych meds. They
wanted to do everything and when I would
visit, they wouldn't allow my mom to
take a picture. I was just in a cell 23
and 1
and gave birth to and didn't even see
him. Didn't even know who he was.
And it's crazy cuz that's one part that
I of my incarceration that I said I
would never talk about, but my son said
it was okay for me to talk about.
He is in my life now. My son is home.
Um
he knew he knew of me he said when he
turned 11, 12. So, he looked for me. And
he found me when I came home.
The white had the most beautiful church
you could ever see. Then they got the
school building which is James Adam
Hall. We got nail tech, we got the hair
salon. Get your hair permed, you get
your hair straightened, you your nails
done, get your toes done. I mean, so
it's the same thing. Same thing that
goes on out here. You get that inside.
It annoys you by perfume in that bottle
in the commissary. Color pencils, I used
to do makeup with my my watercolor
pencils. You buy the the hair products
if you want a perm or whatever, you have
to pay for that. And the nail tech is
no, they they use you as a student. They
use you as a model. But your hair, you
do have to pay. It's all inmate base. Um
they go to school and they get certified
or people come to It's come to prison
already certified.
I went to the school. I went to the Lady
College. Um I did get my GED after my
mother passed away.
I wasn't supposed to.
I wasn't even allowed back in the
school.
I had jumped on the teacher.
>> What did you do to that teacher
initially, if you don't mind?
>> Oh Lord. Um Miss Reed was very
aggressive when it came to the inmates.
Oh, you're stupid. Oh, you don't know
this right. Ooh.
And I was just called somebody stupid.
And I end up getting a chair hitting her
across the back. And damn, I broke the
lady's back.
So, I was banned from school for the
rest of my sentence.
16 years later, my mother passed away.
And I went back and I said, I I wanted
to so bad prove to my mom that I can do
this.
I begged my teacher. I begged her. I
said, "Miss Reed, can you please let me
come back and get my G?" She said, "No."
She said, "I cannot do that. They don't
want you in the school. You did what you
did to me.
I was like, "Please, Miss Reed. My momma
dead. I got to show her I can get it."
And I remember her saying, "If you
graduate
I'm going to be the one to give you your
certificate." Now, mind you, I hadn't
been to school in 16 years. And I was so
determined because this is what I wanted
for my mom.
So, I ended up getting my GED. I went to
restaurant management,
dog grooming, dog training, to computer
tech. So, it is a lot of vocational, but
that was in Dwight. When they shut
Dwight down, they went to Logan.
The lifers couldn't go to school like
that. The lifers were not allowed to go
to school.
It was only for people who had
an outdate.
And that was the messed up thing about
it cuz I used to tell myself, "I'm going
to go to court and I'm going to get an
outdate. So, you're not going to let me
finish the rest of my management because
I'm a lifer."
But, lifers get out, too.
That blesses I mean, laws change every
day.
And I wasn't allowed to finish my rest
of my management. This should be
rehabilitation, but it's not. And I
always make I always considered Dwight
my home. When we was going When we was
getting locked down and being
transferred to um Lincoln, I cried like
a baby.
I cried so hard. I felt like I was being
kicked out of my home.
And it was a hard pill to swallow. And
when you see all on order, you're
watching other prison movies,
please don't expect to think that it's
for real. No, it's not. I mean, I hate
that that prison I wish prison some of
the prisons were like that because I do
have a niece and who's also on probation
right now cuz she got caught with a gun.
I wish she was fearful of prison, but of
course she's not because she's been in
prison to see me. So, she's seen the
hair getting done and the nails. And so,
she's seen this.
What had changed my life is when my mom
passed away. I knew that I had messed up
and forgot to make it right before my
mom died. I wanted to change up. I
wanted to I wanted to bury Loc today. I
did. I wanted to
become Jacqueline.
Graduate from college and I did all
that. I did all that before my mom. I
decided to get up the game life because
it wasn't in me no more. I never thought
that I would live to see past 16. I
didn't. I had my funeral arrangements
ready for age 16.
But here I am, about to be 50 years old.
I can't be a gang member or glorify with
what I did in my life. Glorify my
murders when I'm trying to help people
not make the same mistake. And
then Northwestern came into my life.
Northwestern law center a law school It
was Bluhm Legal Clinic. It was 2013 when
the when he still was trying to get me
back in court. The law changed. People
Miller versus Alabama
and was able to change law saying that
juveniles could no longer be sentenced
to life in prison as a juvenile. They
made it retroactive. So, because of that
it gave me a chance to be resentenced.
Those were the ones who called me and
told me like, "Bro, there's a new case
out.
There's a new case in in the computer
home." I was like, "Get me home. This is
my home. What are you talking about?" I
kept arguing with them arguing with them
every time they called.
I would tell them, "I'm not going
anywhere. This is my home. Stop doing
it."
I went back to county jail on March 3rd,
2015 to be resentenced. And the victim's
family got on the stand and said, "Why
he shouldn't be resentenced?" And why he
should be sentenced to life in prison
again and woo woo. And I stood there and
watched them.
And and the pain they felt I felt.
When it was my turn to speak before I
got sentenced,
the victim's family all got up and left.
So, they weren't even there to listen to
my statement.
And that kind of blew me. I cried like a
baby. I apologized for what I did. I
agreed with them. And I told them, "I'm
I'm with you. I don't agree that I
should be sentenced to nothing other
than life prison.
I mean, I'm agreeing with you. But
I went ahead and played out for 63
years. And they ended up telling me that
I had to do 7 and 1/2 more years or
whatever, which it wasn't. It wasn't
even that long because of the fact that
when I was a lifer I couldn't get good
days. I couldn't do I couldn't get no
credit for my GED. I couldn't get credit
for college classes and all that. But
now that I had access to three years, I
was able to get all that credit. So,
instead of doing 7 and 1/2 years,
I ended up coming home with a year and a
half early. I was scared that I was
going to get my update stuck.
I was scared that I wasn't going to want
to leave
because all my friends and family were
there.
So,
I ended up paying $3,000
to be transferred to Interstate Compact
to be transferred to Florida prison.
>> 80% of people at that prison had tested
positive for COVID at one time.
>> They did. They did. Florida
Florida was was I saw everybody getting
sick. I watched a lot of people die
behind that COVID. My
bunkie died. They thought she was
sleeping, she was dead.
Thank God I never caught it. I think God
that me being in Interstate Compact,
that the minute it was a break out they
put me in confinement until I got my
shots
and was released.
But, I saw I was never really had I
wouldn't have contact to COVID because
of that.
But,
as I got released and after I had I was
the only person in in the institution
that got my shots because my shots came
from Illinois.
So,
they turned around and I watched people
literally die.
Like, and I couldn't believe it.
I thought the world was coming to an
end.
I got released in Ocala, Florida
and it was April 1st, 2022. And I
remember crying and crying.
I just fell on the floor.
I couldn't sleep.
Why? Why am I here and not them? Why was
I released and not nobody else?
So, it was hard. It was a hard day. It
was a happy and a hard day. They took me
to a seafood place cuz I had never ate
lobster or crab legs. I was like, I'm
going to do everything I I never did in
my life. Everything I was told that I
couldn't do, I wanted to do. So, my
first thing was eat seafood.
And boy, was I embarrassed. So, I
remember them bringing these big ass
crab legs and and lobster. I'm like,
what the
And I didn't know that I had to take a
shell out. I didn't know what I was
doing.
Everybody started laughing at me. I was
like, what's wrong? They were like, "You
got the plier thing right there because
that's what's going to grab." I said,
"Oh."
I didn't know.
But, it was a bittersweet.
When I first came home, I had to
I put bars in my window.
I was scared. For the first year,
for the first year of my freedom, I was
still adjusting. I didn't want to go
outside. I was scared. I didn't even use
metal sport I was still using plastic
forks. I was still adjusting. I didn't
I was still getting up thinking it was
chow time. I was still fear, a lot of
fear
um that I was going to get killed.
Due to my case,
I sent my niece to the store. She came
from Chicago to visit me in Florida.
And um we was in the store and I didn't
thought nothing of it. And I'm seeing
that the machines are empty. So I'm
telling my niece, "Well, go grab that
machine right quick so we can go ahead
and pay for it." As she was trying to go
there, this other lady pushed her
daughter there and was like, "No, I I
was in line." I was like, "Okay, my bad.
Okay, fine." I was like, "You know, go
get the other machine." So when she went
to get the other machine, she pushed her
same daughter to the other machine.
I said, "Now you being like we ain't
going to play these games no more." I
was ready to fight. I was ready
I was waiting for her outside. My niece
was like, "No, Z Z, don't go back to
prison." And it was like and I had to
look at her face and she was starting to
cry. And I was just like, "Oh my god,
I'm not used to this." It was something
new. But I felt like she was trying me.
And in prison, you don't try nobody. Now
you trying me, now I got to show who I
am. So I had to remember this is not
prison. Cuz I was ready to whoop that
girl butt behind. I waited outside for a
while until my niece cried away like,
"Let's just go home. Let's just go
home."
I spent more time in prison than I did
in the free world.
So after 31 years in prison, there would
be days that I still feel like I should
be in prison. What I would tell my
younger me,
don't give up.
Second chances are real. I just recently
got out and I'm got my own apartment. So
I'm I'm still learning. I'm still making
mistakes, y'all. It's not I'm not I'm
not I'm human. I'm not no angel. I'm
human. And I'm still making mistakes. I
lost I gave birth to two babies that
were dead and I lost my way.
So I had to find my way back. And that's
why I want I want people to know that
people we do change.
We do change. We grow up. Yeah, I
committed I did commit the murders. I
did do what they said I did. But I'm not
who they say I am.
I mentor the kids.
um
just trying to help them not make the
same mistakes that I made.
A lot of people in prison they say
they're innocent.
Everybody says they didn't do anything.
Well, I'm the opposite. I'm guilty.
I committed a double murder.
I pulled the trigger.
I watched these men die.
So, my goal is today is I can't bring
them back. May they rest in peace. I
can't bring them back.
And sometimes I wish I could change
places with them.
Cuz they had family and I didn't. So,
right now I have my goal in life to give
back to them and to give back to society
for the mistakes that I've made is I try
to help these youth not make the same
mistakes I made. I'm actually working
with the Lighthouse Church
where is independent living.
And they have three houses now in
Chicago, Illinois who are accepting
anybody. This is like a second chance
program. I'm looking at trying to get a
building
so that I can open up uh
dog room and dog training. So, that the
youth could come inside my building.
Instead of being out there robbing
people, selling drugs, getting in
trouble, they can come into my building
for free
and learn how to do learn how to groom a
dog, learn how to basic training a dog.
And dogs are very therapeutic. So, that
is my goal to do that. I do have a spot
fund me
um where I'm collecting donations so
that I can be able to do that.
We're actually fighting now to change
some stuff at at Lincoln Correctional
Center and Logan Correctional Center.
Logan prison is messed up because they
keep saying that you want to
rehabilitate these inmates, but yet
there's no classes to do that. Actually,
the women are down there dying.
They're getting sick. We're coming home
and realize we're fighting cancer. I
fought cancer. There's no good health
right health system there.
But, a A of things need to change.
Rehabilitation is one of them. Reentry
is another one. Show these people that
what they are capable of coming home to
and what to do with it because nobody
taught me how to come home and do
anything. So, I was left with no family
members and nothing to to to I couldn't
get a job. I still can't get a job
because
they do a background check or apartments
they do a background checks and and
score and a
credit score. I don't know anything
about that, but you have to get reentry.
You have to give these people second
chances or they have to or they're going
to go back to what they know to survive.
So, reentry is the number one thing that
I would love to see in these prisons and
it starts in the prison and then it
comes out here.
This is my juvenile life without parole.
In the back it says clemency for
Jacqueline.
This is a shirt that so many people wore
trying to fight to get me home. They
went in front of the parole boards.
Northwestern Blue Clinic is amazing. I
have met a lot of people inside prisons
to come see me just to give me a second
chance. So, this shirt means a lot
because there's still people inside now.
There's kids still today being charged
as an adult trying to get sentenced to
life in prison. That's why I said my
program Future for Tomorrow's Youth is a
big issue because the system is really
failing us, y'all.
Juvenile life without parole, can you
imagine?
Can you imagine your niece, your nephew,
your child being at the wrong place at
the wrong time?
Cuz you don't even have to pull the
trigger.
My co-defendant didn't pull the trigger.
Yes, she was sentenced to the death
penalty.
My other co-defendant didn't pull the
trigger. Yes, she was sentenced to 35
years in prison.
It has to put a stop to it.
>> Hi, I'm a producer on How Crime Works.
If you like this video, please subscribe
and comment below with more topics that
that would like us to cover.